A Finding Aid to the Theodoros Stamos papers, circa 1922-2008, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Theodoros Stamos papers
circa 1922-2008
Archives of American Art
Stamos, Theodoros, 1922-1997
AAA.stamtheo
Archival Resource Key
3.1 Linear feet
The papers of Theodoros Stamos measure 3.1 linear feet and date from circa 1922-2008. Stamos was a painter primarily associated with the first generation of Abstract Expressionists. Biographical materials, correspondence, writings, business and legal records, printed materials, and photographs document Stamos' career as a painter. Also included are materials relating to the Rothko estate controversy compiled by Stamos' sister, Georgianna Savas, as well as her papers concerning arrangements for Stamos' funeral and posthumous exhibition plans.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Theodoros Stamos loaned the Archives of American Art material for microfilming in 1970. Stamos' sister, Georgianna Savas, donated papers in 2008 and 2011.
Separated Material
The Archives of American Art also holds materials lent for microfilming (reels N70-66 and N70-67) including correspondence, poems, printed material and membership cards. Lent material was returned to the lender and is not described in the collection container inventory.
Related Material
Among the holdings of the Archives of American Art are oral history interveiws conducted by John Jones and Bruce Hooten, February 19, 1965, and by Irving Sandler, April 23, 1968. Also found are Theodoros Stamos letters to Diran Deckmejian, 1977-1995, and Theodoros Stamos letters to James DiMartino, 1977-1988.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical Note
Painter Theodoros Stamos (1922-1997) worked in New York and spent considerable time in Lefkada, Greece. A first generation Abstract Expressionist, Stamos developed as a color field painter, and had a long teaching career. His later years were encumbered by his role in the Mark Rothko Estate controversy.
Born to Greek immigrant parents in New York City, Stamos attended the prestigious Stuyvesant High School, leaving just three months before graduation to pursue a career in art. From 1941 to 1948 he operated a frame shop where he framed hundreds of Paul Klee paintings for Nierendorf Gallery and encountered customers such as Arshile Gorky and Fernand Léger, experiences that influenced the young artist.
Stamos' first solo exhibition, presented by Betty Parsons in 1943, brought the 20 year old painter to the attention of museums and private collectors. Throughout the 1940s Stamos painted and traveled extensively. By the end of the decade he had had three solo exhibitions and participated in group shows such as the 1945 Whitney Museum Biennial and "The Ideographic Picture," an important early Abstract Expressionist exhibition curated by Barnett Newman.
Through connections made at the American Artists' School Stamos became a notable artist among the New York avant garde during the early years of Abstract Expressionism. He was the youngest of the "Irascibles," a group of American artists who broke from the School of Paris to create a new approach to abstract painting.
In 1951, Stamos built a house in East Marion, New York on Long Island where he lived and worked. Here, he began to develop his color field technique and, influenced by his Greek heritage, continued to express interest in spiritualism and ancient Greek myths and philosophy. In 1958, Stamos' work was shown in a retrospective exhibition at the Corcoran Gallery of Art, Washington, DC, and in "The New American Painting," the Museum of Modern Art's traveling exhibition that introduced European audiences to Abstract Expressionism.
Stamos began his career as an educator in 1950 at Black Mountain College. Later, he taught at Columbia University and Brandeis University, and for more than 20 years was on the faculty of the Art Students League.
Following the death of his friend Mark Rothko, Stamos was involved in a highly publicized lawsuit involving his role as an executor of the estate. The trial ended unsuccessfully for Stamos and its adverse consequences impacted the late part of his career. In 1966, the Rothko children obtained permission to disinter their father's remains from the Stamos burial plot in East Marion, New York; with the assistance of Stamos' sister, Georgianna Savas, arrangements were made to bury Rothko at a cemetery in Valhalla, New York.
Traveling between homes in New York and Lefkada, Greece, Stamos continued to paint and teach late into his life. He died in Greece in 1997.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Theodoros Stamos measure 3.1 linear feet and date from circa 1922-2008. Stamos was a painter primarily associated with the first generation of Abstract Expressionists. Biographical materials, correspondence, writings, business and legal records, printed materials, and photographs document Stamos' career as a painter. Also included are materials relating to the Rothko estate controversy compiled by Stamos' sister, Georgianna Savas, as well as her papers concerning arrangements for Stamos' funeral and posthumous exhibition plans.
Biographical material includes birth and death certificates and interview transcripts. Personal correspondence is with friends and family; professional correspondence pertains to gallery transactions, including a falling out with gallery owner Louis K. Meisel. Among the printed materials are exhibition announcements and clippings of articles in English and Greek concerning his career and personal life. Photographs include views of family and friends, portraits of Stamos by Hans Namuth, Nina Leen and other photographers, as well as images of artwork by Stamos and other artists.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 9 series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1922-2006 (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 2: Financial Records, 1979-circa 1990s (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 3: Correspondence, circa 1940s-1997 (Boxes 1, 5; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 4: Business and Legal, 1974-2008 (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 5: Writings, circa 1944-2002 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 6: Artwork, circa 1940s-1980 (Box 1, OV 6-7; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 7: Printed Materials, 1945-2007 (Box 2, OV 7; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 8: Photographs, 1943-1999 (Boxes 2-3, 5; 1.0 linear feet)
Series 9: Georgianna Savas Papers on Theodoros Stamos, 1985-2005 (Boxes 3-4; 0.3 linear feet)
Existence and Location of Copies
Materials lent for microfilming are available on 35mm microfilm reels N70-66 and N70-67 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan.
Transcripts; Photographs; Abstract expressionism; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Painting, American; Painting -- Technique; Interviews; Namuth, Hans; Savas, Georgianna; Meisel, Louis K.; Leen, Nina, 1909-; Rothko, Mark, 1903-1970
- Biographical Material, circa 1922-2006; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical materials include birth and death certificates, membership cards, two address books with contact information for artists such as Willem de Kooning and Mark Rothko, and interview transcripts. There are three versions of the Stamos will, including the final draft in which he left the majority of his estate to his sister, Georgianna Savas. Also included are a VHS video cassette of Stamos' memorial service, memorabilia, and a plaque awarded posthumously by a Greek organization.
  - Address Books, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Birth Certificate, 1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Curriculum Vitae, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Membership and Insurance Cards, 1987-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Interview Transcripts, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Death Certificate, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Last Will and Testament, 1982-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Obituary and Memorial Service, 1997; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Award, 2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Financial Records, 1979-circa 1990's; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders Box 1
  This series contains records of art sales made by Louis K. Meisel Gallery. Also found are a check book register and a receipt for canvas.
  - Photocopies of checks to Theodoros Stamos from Louis K. Meisel Gallery, 1979-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Check Register and Receipt, circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, circa 1940s-1997; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 1, 5
  Correspondence documents business dealings with museums and galleries that represented Stamos. Also found are letters from E. W. Root, director of Black Mountain College and an early collector of Abstract Expressionist art, a collaged Christmas card from Helen Frankenthaler, and personal letters and notes.
  - Correspondence, circa 1940s-1997; Archival Resource Key; 7 Folders (Box 1, Folder 12-18)
    Oversized material housed in box 5
  - ACA Galleries, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Camillos Kouros Gallery, 1988-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Galleria D'Arte del Naviglio, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Gallery Lambert Monet, 1979-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Louis K. Meisel Gallery, 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - P.T. Efstathiou Fine Arts, 1992-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Tanger Gallery, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Gallery Veith Turske, 1979-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Oversized Correspondence, circa 1940s-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 5)
    from box 1, folders 12-18
- Business and Legal Records, 1974-2008; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders Box 1
  Business and legal records include the estate and final tax records for Theodoros Stamos as well as petitions and legal documents regarding the disinternment of Mark Rothko from the Stamos burial plot in East Marion, NY.
  - Theodoros Stamos Estate Records, 1997-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Mark Rothko Estate Records, 1974-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Writings, circa 1944-2002; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  This series contains an artist's statement and personal notes including price lists for works of art. Writings about Stamos by others include a chronology of Stamos' life through 1970, a 1960 interview with Lawrence Alloway for Art News and Review, and a documentary film proposal that include Stamos and his work.
  - By Theodoros Stamos, circa 1944-1980; undated; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
  - By Other Authors about Theodoros Stamos, 1960-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Artwork, circa 1940s-1980; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1, OV 6-7
  This series contains artwork by Stamos such as line drawings, collages and small paintings. Also included are a handmade card and drawings by other artists, and illustrated rocks attributed to Stamos and gallery owner, Betty Parsons.
  - Drawings and Paintings by Theodoros Stamos, 1947-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Drawings and Cards by Other Artists, undated; 1950; 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Illustrations on Rocks, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Oversized Sketches and Drawings, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 6)
  - Oversized Designs for Posters, 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 7)
- Printed Materials, 1945-2007; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 2, OV 7
  This series contains clippings and exhibition announcements in both English and Greek, relating to Stamos and his artwok, and to other Abstract Expressionists. Posthumous announcements were collected by Georgianna Savas and are mostly from shows of his work that she arranged. Some clippings concern the Rothko Estate controversy and the disinternment of Rothko's remains from Stamos' burial plot.
  - Clippings about Theodoros Stamos, undated; 1947-2008; Archival Resource Key; 8 Folders (Box 2, Folder 1-8)
  - Clippings of Related Artists, 1958-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Exhibition Checklist, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Brochures, 1947-2005; undated; Archival Resource Key; 8 Folders (Box 2, Folder 11-18)
  - Reproductions, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Offprints, 1948-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Items, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
    - Relating to Others, 2002; 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Relating to Memorial Service, 1997; 2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Oversized Posters, 1966-1978; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 7)
  - Oversized Lecture Announcements, 1964 April 8 or 1970 April 8; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 7)
- Photographs, 1943-1999; Series 8; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Boxes 2-3, 5
  This series includes photographs of Stamos, his family, his homes and studios in New York and Greece, and works of art. Most photographs are unattributed, but photographs by Han Namuth, Lloyd Lozes Goff, Steven Trefonides and Diran Deckmejian (a former student at the Art Students League) are found along with a group photograph of the "Irascibles" taken by Nina Leen for Life magazine in 1950. Other photographs document Stamos late in life, his memorial service and grave dedication, and views of posthumous retrospective exhibitions.
  - Artwork, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
    - Theodoros Stamos, A-Z, and unidentified (executed circa 1947-1967), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Theodoros Stamos, undated; 1994-1999; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders (Box 2, Folder 24-27)
    - Other Artists, undated; 1999; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Other Artists, Evelyn Jablow interior with Stamos Painting, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Events, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
    - Theodoros Stamos on Lecture Panel, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
      oversized material housed in box 5
    - ACA Gallery Exhibition Opening, 1993; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Hiro Gallery Exhibition Opening, 1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Theodoros Stamos with Friends; Gallery Opening, circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Theodoros Stamos Funeral in Lefkada, Greece, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Retrospective Opening and Monument Commemoration in Greece, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Theodoros Stamos Memorial Service, New York City, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - People, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
    - Portraits of Theodoros Stamos, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
      - Lloyd Lozes Goff, 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - Diran Deckmejian, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - Hans Namuth, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - Steven Trefonides, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - Bill Wilson, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - Unidentified Photographers, undated; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders (Box 2, Folder 42-45)
        Oversized material housed in Box 5
    - Group Portrait of the "Irascibles" including Stamos by Nina Leen, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Informal Images of Theodoros Stamos, 1943-1978; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Theodoros Stamos with Family and Friends, undated; 1961-1997; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders (Box 2, Folder 48-49)
    - Theodoros Stamos with Friends at Party, 1992; circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders (Box 2, Folder 50-51)
    - Friends, Gavin Arthur and Robert Price, undated; 1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Friends, Family and Others, undated; 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Colleagues, circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Family and Friends in Greece, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Places, Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
    - Construction of the Stamos House in East Marion, New York, 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Theodoros Stamos' Samosa Studio, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Cemetery; Views of Athens, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Household Interior with Stamos Painting, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - House Under Construction (unidentified location), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
    - Images Collected by Theodoros Stamos, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Slides, Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
    - Artwork by Theodoros Stamos, circa 1947-1987; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Transparencies, Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
    - Artwork by Theodoros Stamos, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Portraits of Theodoros Stamos, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Negatives, Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
    - Artwork by Theodoros Stamos, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
      black and white
    - Artwork by Theodoros Stamos, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
      color
    - Monument and Family in Greece, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Cemetery views, Athens and Memorial Service, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Oversized Photographs, Archival Resource Key (Box 5)
    - Artwork, 1999; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5)
      from box 2, folder 28
    - Events, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5)
      from box 2, folder 30
    - People, circa 1960s; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5)
      from box 2, folders 40, 42-46
    - Images Collected by Stamos, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5)
      from box 4, folder 6
    - Stamos Monument, 1997 or later; Archival Resource Key (Box 5)
- Georgianna Savas Papers on Theodoros Stamos, 1985-2005; Series 9; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 3-4
  This series contains Georgianna Savas' papers relating to her brother, Theodoros Stamos. Found are notes and correspondence about the handling of the Stamos estate and correspondence concerning the Stamos retrospective exhibition at the National Gallery of Greece organized by Savas. There is correspondence relating to the exhumation of the Rothko remains from the Stamos family plot in East Marion, New York and records concerning cleaning and conservation services for Stamos' painting. Condolence cards received by Savas after the death of her brother are also part of this series.
  - Notebook, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Records, Conservation Receipts, undated; 1985-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
    - Relating to Theodoros Stamos, 1986-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Relating to Theodoros Stamos Exhibition in Greece, 1996-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Condolence Cards, 1997; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Notes, Stamos Estate, 1999; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
    - Foundation for Hellenic Culture Exhibition Opening, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Stamos Foundation Exhibition Installation, Transportation and Unidentified People, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Marymount Exhibition Installation and Book Signing, 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)